Charles W. Barrow papers, Inclusive: 1939-2006, undated, Bulk: 1972-1984
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Charles W. Barrow papers
Inclusive: 1939-2006, undated, Bulk: 1972-1984
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
3
Barrow, Charles W., 1921 - 2006
9 document boxes, 3 oversize boxes
The Charles Barrow papers include campaign materials, photographs, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, newsletters, and memorandums. A bulk of the material is dated 1977-1984, the period Barrow served as Texas Supreme Court Justice.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Charles W. Barrow was born September 22, 1921, in Poteet, Texas. He spent his youth in Atascosa, primarily in Jourdanton. Barrow graduated from the Baylor University School of Law in 1943 after which he joined the US Navy during World War II. He was active in the Pacific and European theaters, notably during the Normandy invasion, and earned seven battle stars. Barrow also served during the Korean War, retired as Captain, then continued to serve in the Navy Reserves until 1976.
In 1945, Barrow began practicing law in San Antonio, Texas, and by 1959, became a District Judge of the 45th Judicial District Court. Judge Barrow was appointed to the 4th Court of Civil Appeals in 1962, to fill the unexpired term left by the death of his father, Judge Hunter Barrow. In 1967, Charles Barrow was elected to the 4th Court of Civil Appeals and served in the position until 1977, the year he was appointed to the Texas Supreme Court.
Judge Barrow was twice elected to the Supreme Court, once in 1978, and again in 1982. While serving as Justice, Barrow received several accolades, including the Distinguished Jurist Gavel Award from the St. Mary’s University School of Law in 1978, the Greenhill Judicial Award from the Texas Municipal Courts Association in 1979, and the Distinguished Alumni award given by his alma mater, Baylor University, in 1982.
Justice Barrow resigned his position on the Texas Supreme Court to fill the post as Dean of the Baylor School of Law. He served in this capacity from 1984-1991. In 1991, he returned on a part-time basis as a Senior District Judge in San Antonio until his retirement in 1996. Barrow was widely regarded as a hard worker, evidenced by his 700+ written court opinions. Charles W. Barrow passed on June 25, 2006.
Charles Barrow was married to the former Sugie Williams. They had four sons, Charles Wallace (Wally), Jr., John Douglas, David Williams, and James Hunter.
Scope and Content
The Charles W. Barrow papers, dated 1939-2006, include campaign materials, photographs, scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, and memorandums.
The Personal series includes General items such as family papers, military records, correspondence, event programs, and newspaper clippings. Also included are memorials and condolences kept by the Barrow family after the death of their son, Wally. The Campaigns subseries includes correspondence, general publications, and newspaper clippings. The clippings are of note due to their focus on Barrow’s opponents, Woodrow Wilson Bean and Don Yarbrough. The Certificates and Awards subseries contains diplomas, certificates, and other recognitions given to Barrow.
The Photographs and Scrapbooks series includes personal family photographs and photos taken while Barrow was a justice. Several scrapbooks are included and highlight his appointment as judge to the 45th District Court in San Antonio and several other judgeships. The Texas Supreme Court series contains Applications for Writ of Error presented while Barrow was a justice. Newsletters and Judicial Yearbooks are also present.
Arrangement
Previous inventories and finding aids were arranged in 1991, 1995, 1998, and 2000. The most recent arrangement has been reorganized to include three series: Personal, Photographs and Scrapbooks, and Texas Supreme Court. The Personal series is further divided into General, Campaigns, and Certificates and Awards.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3. Acquired 1991-10-04
Related Resources
Related references
“Baylor Mourns Former Law Dean and ‘Legal Giant’ Justice Charles W. Barrow.” Baylor Media Communications. Accessed November 8, 2018.
“Charles W. Barrow.” Texas State Cemetery. Accessed November 8, 2018.
Charles W. Barrow Papers, Accession #3, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W. R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
“Justices of Texas 1836-1986: Charles W. Barrow.” Tarlton Law Library Jamail Center for Legal Research. Accessed November 8, 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Barrow, Charles W., 1921-2006.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University. Law School -- Faculty.; Texas. Supreme Court.
Subjects
Judges -- Texas.
Genres
Albums (Books); Awards.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Diplomas.; Memorandums.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Programs (Publications).; Records (Documents); Yearbooks.
- Personal, 1941-2006, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Personal series is dated 1941-2006 and includes three subseries: General, Campaigns, and Certificates and Awards. The General subseries includes military records, event programs, items related to Barrow’s tenure as Dean of the Baylor University School of Law, and memorials for his son, Wally. Newspaper clippings are also included.
  The Campaigns subseries includes items related to Judge Barrow’s run for the Texas Supreme Court. Publicity materials, correspondence, and newspaper clippings are present. Clippings may be of interest as they highlight Barrow’s opponents Woodrow Wilson Bean and the controversial Don Yarbrough.
  The Certificates and Awards subseries includes items of recognition, guest speaker certificates, and items related to Barrow’s time at Baylor. Baylor items include undergraduate diplomas, faculty certificates, distinguished Alumni awards, and golden anniversary diplomas for Barrow and his wife Sugie.
  Each subseries is arranged chronologically and the series is in good condition.
  - General, 1941-1997, undated; 1
    - Ben Sargent Cartoons, undated (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Family Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Military Records, World War II (RESTRICTED), 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Baylor University Handbook for Dormitory Women (Copy), 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Military Records, Korea (RESTRICTED), 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Biographical Information, 1960-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Military Records, Naval Reserves Promotion and Retirement, 1965, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Baylor Law Day, Lawyer of the Year, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - News Clippings, Judge, 1972-1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - News Clippings, 1974-2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Programs, Judge, 1975-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Programs, 1975-2007 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dean of Baylor University School of Law, 1984-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Baylor University Law School, 1984-1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Charles Wallace “Wally” Barrow, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Baylor Commencement Program, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Newsletters, 1993 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 2)
    - Presentation of Supreme Court Portrait, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Campaigns, 1962-1982, undated; 2
    - Publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - News clippings, publicity, finances, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, Texas Supreme Court, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - News clippings, Don Yarbrough, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Publicity, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - News clippings, Don Yarbrough, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - News clippings, Don Yarbrough, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Texas Supreme Court, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Endorsements, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - News clippings, Woodrow Wilson Bean, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Publicity, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1943-2006, undated; 3
    - Baylor Alumni Association Life Member, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General, 1943-1973 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 3)
    - Baylor University Diplomas, 1943-1991 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 4)
    - Supreme Court, 1956 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 5)
    - Law Firm Partnership, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Recognitions, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lions Club Guest Speaker, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Faculty Certificates, 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Distinguished Alumni, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Faculty Certificates, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Golden Anniversary Diploma, Charles Wallace Barrow, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Golden Anniversary Diploma, Sugie Williams Barrow, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Memorial Senate Proclamation 747, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1939-2003, undated; 2
  The Photographs and Scrapbooks series is dated 1939-2003. This series is mostly personal in nature. It includes military photographs and early photos of Sugie, Barrow’s wife. Other photos include items from Charles Barrow’s tenure on the Texas Supreme Court, family events, and real estate photos from the house he occupied in Fort Faculty while Dean of the Baylor School of Law. Scrapbooks are also included. They document Barrow’s career from his first appointment as a judge in San Antonio and beyond. This series is ordered chronologically and in good condition.
  - State Supreme Court Campaign, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Realty Estate Appraisal, 200 Guittard, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sugie “Williams” Barrow, 1939-1943 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Navy, circa 1943 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Career Scrapbook, 1954-1977 (Box 11 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Judges Appointment and Congratulations Scrapbook, 1959 (Box 12 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Club (1 of 6), 1958-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Club (2 of 6), 1958-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Club (3 of 6), 1958-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Club (4 of 6), 1958-1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Club (5 of 6), 1958-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Club (6 of 6), 1958-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Austin Supreme Court (1 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Austin Supreme Court (2 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Austin Supreme Court (3 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Austin Supreme Court (4 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Austin Supreme Court (5 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Austin Supreme Court (6 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Austin Supreme Court (7 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Austin Supreme Court (8 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Austin Supreme Court (9 of 9), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Barrow, Texas Supreme Court, circa 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Family Scrapbook, 1979-1993 (Box 12 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Baylor (1 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Baylor (2 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Baylor (3 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Baylor (4 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Baylor (5 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Baylor (6 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Baylor (7 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Baylor (8 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Baylor (9 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Baylor (10 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Baylor (11 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Baylor (12 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Baylor (13 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Baylor (14 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Baylor (15 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Baylor (16 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Baylor (17 of 17), 1983-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Friends and Family (1 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Friends and Family (2 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Friends and Family (3 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Friends and Family (4 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Friends and Family (5 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Friends and Family (6 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Friends and Family (7 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Friends and Family (8 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Friends and Family (9 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Friends and Family (10 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Friends and Family (11 of 11), 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Texas Supreme Court, 1960-1984, undated; 3
  The Texas Supreme Court series is dated 1960-1984. This series includes a personal memo book, two judicial yearbooks, and newsletters. The bulk of this series is memorandums concerning Applications for Writ of Error reviewed by Judge Barrow and other justices. Each session from 1977-1984, is represented and includes the following information: nature of the case, jurisdiction, facts, points of error, discussion, and disposition. This series is in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Memorandum Book, Marriage Ceremony, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Judicial Yearbook, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Judicial Yearbook (1 of 2), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Judicial Yearbook (2 of 2), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1974 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters, 1976-1985 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 2), 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 2), 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 6), 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 6), 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (3 of 6), 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (4 of 6), 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (5 of 6), 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (6 of 6), 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 4), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 4), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (3 of 4), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (4 of 4), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 3), 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 3), 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Applications for Writ of Error, (3 of 3), 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 4), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 4), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (3 of 4), 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (4 of 4), 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 3), 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 3), 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (3 of 3), 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (1 of 2), 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Applications for Writ of Error (2 of 2), 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Applications for Writ of Error, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 3)